Can geographic information
هل يمكن لمعلومات الجغرافيا
make you healthy?
أن تجعلك صحيحاً؟
In 2001 I got hit by a train.
عام 2001 صدمني قطار.
My train was a heart attack.
القطار كان سكتة قلبية.
I found myself in a hospital
وجدت نفسي في مستشفى
in an intensive-care ward,
في العناية المركزة،
recuperating from emergency surgery.
أتعافى من عملية جراحية طارئة.
And I suddenly realized something:
وفجأة أدركت شيئا:
that I was completely in the dark.
كان سابقاً في الظلام تماماً.
I started asking my questions, "Well, why me?"
بدأت بطرح أسئلتي، "حسناً، لماذا أنا؟"
"Why now?" "Why here?"
"لماذا الآن؟" "لماذا هنا؟"
"Could my doctor have warned me?"
"هل كان بإمكان طبيبي أن يحذرني؟"
So, what I want to do here in the few minutes I have with you
إذاً، ما أريد فعله هنا في الدقائق القليلة التي لدي معكم
is really talk about what is the formula for life and good health.
هو الحديث حول ماهية صيغة الحياة، والصحة الجيدة،
Genetics, lifestyle and environment.
الجينات، أسلوب الحياة والبيئة.
That's going to sort of contain our risks,
وسيحوي هذا بعض مخاطرنا،
and if we manage those risks
وإذا قمنا بإدارة تلك المخاطر
we're going to live a good life and a good healthy life.
سنحيا حياة جيدة، وحياة صحية جيدة.
Well, I understand the genetics and lifestyle part.
حسناً، أنا أفهم جزئي الجينات وأسلوب الحياة.
And you know why I understand that?
وأنتم تعلمون لماذا أفهم ذلك؟
Because my physicians constantly
لأن طبيبي باستمرار
ask me questions about this.
يسألني أسئلة حول هذا.
Have you ever had to fill out those long,
هل سبق وأن ملئت هذه طويلاً،
legal-size forms in your doctor's office?
أوراق قانونية في مكتب طبيبك؟
I mean, if you're lucky enough you get to do it more than once, right?
أعني، إذا كنت محظوظاً بما يكفي ستفعل هذا أكثر من مرة، صحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Do it over and over again. And they ask you questions
تفعلها مراراً وتكراراً. ويسألونك أسئلة
about your lifestyle and your family history,
حول أسلوب حياتك وتاريخ أسرتك،
your medication history, your surgical history,
تاريخك حالتك الطبية، تاريخ عملياتك الجراحية،
your allergy history ... did I forget any history?
تاريخ الحساسيات...هل نسيت أي تاريخ؟
But this part of the equation I didn't really get,
لكن هذا الجزء من المعادلة لم أفهمه.
and I don't think my physicians
ولا أعتقد أن أطبائي المعالجين
really get this part of the equation.
حقاً فهموا هذا الجزء من المعادلة.
What does that mean, my environment?
ماذا يعني ذلك، بيئتي؟
Well, it can mean a lot of things.
حسناً، يمكن أن تعني الكثير من الأشياء.
This is my life. These are my life places.
هذه هي حياتي. هذه الأماكن التي عشت فيها.
We all have these.
لدينا جميعاً هذه.
While I'm talking I'd like you to also be thinking about:
بينما أتحدث أرغب في التفكير أيضاً حول
How many places have you lived?
كم عدد الأماكن التي عشتوا فيها؟
Just think about that, you know, wander through
فكروا بهذا الأمر، تعرفون، هيموا خلال
your life thinking about this.
حياتكم في التفكير حول هذا الأمر.
And you realize that you spend it in a variety of different places.
وستدركون أنكم قضيتموها في عدة أماكن مختلفة .
You spend it at rest and you spend it at work.
سواء قضيتموها في الراحة أو العمل.
And if you're like me, you're in an airplane a good portion of your time
وإذا كنتم مثلي، في طائرة لجزء كبير من وقتكم
traveling some place.
تسافرون لمكان ما.
So, it's not really simple
إذاً، الأمر بسيط للغاية
when somebody asks you, "Where do you live, where do you work,
حينما يسألك شخص ما، " أين تعيش، أين تعمل،
and where do you spend all your time?
وأين تقضي كل وقتك؟
And where do you expose yourselves to risks
وأين تعرضوا أنفسكم لمخاطر
that maybe perhaps you don't even see?"
ربما لا تكونوا ترونها حتى؟"
Well, when I have done this on myself,
حسناً، عندما فعلت هذا على نفسي،
I always come to the conclusion
أتوصل دائماً لخلاصة
that I spend about 75 percent of my time
أنني قضيت حوالي 75% كم وقتي
relatively in a small number of places.
في عدد قليل من الأماكن نسبياً.
And I don't wander far from that place
وأنا لا أهيم بعيداً عن ذلك المكان
for a majority of my time,
لمعظم أوقاتي،
even though I'm an extensive global trekker.
رغماً عن أنني أجوب العالم كثيراً.
Now, I'm going to take you on a little journey here.
أنا سأقوم بأخذكم لرحلة قصيرة هنا.
I started off in Scranton, Pennsylvania.
لقد نشأت في سكرانتون بولاية بنسلفانيا.
I don't know if anybody might hail from northeastern Pennsylvania,
لا أعرف إن كان أي شخص ينحدر من شمال شرق بنسلفانيا.
but this is where I spent my first 19 years
لكن هنا حيث قضيت أول 19 عاماً
with my little young lungs.
مع رئتي الصغيرتين.
You know, breathing high concentrations here
تعرفون، تستنشق تركيز عالي هنا
of sulfur dioxide, carbon dioxide
من ثاني أوكسيد الكبريت ، ثاني أوكسيد الكربون
and methane gas,
وغاز الميثان،
in unequal quantities -- 19 years of this.
بكميات متفاوتة -- 19 سنة من هذا.
And if you've been in that part of the country,
وإذا ذهبتم لهذا الجزء من البلاد،
this is what those piles of burning, smoldering coal waste look like.
هذه ما تبدو عليه هذه الأكوام المحروقة من مخلفات الفحم.
So then I decided to leave that part of the world,
إذاً، بعد ذلك قررت مغادرة ذلك الجزء من العالم.
and I was going to go to the mid-west.
وكنت ذاهباً الى وسط الغرب.
OK, so I ended up in Louisville, Kentucky.
حسناً، لذا، أنتهيت في لويس فالي في كنتاكي.
Well, I decided to be neighbors to a place called Rubbertown.
حسناً، قررت أن أكون جاراً لهذا المكان المسمى روبورتاون.
They manufacture plastics. They use large quantities chloroprene
أنهم يصنعّون البلاستيك. يستخدمون كميات ضخمة من
and benzene.
الكلوروبرين والبنزين.
Okay, I spent 25 years, in my middle-age lungs now,
حسناً، قضيت 25 عاماً، في منتصف عمر رئتي الآن،
breathing various concentrations of that.
أستنشق تراكيز مختلفة من ذلك.
And on a clear day it always looked like this, so you never saw it.
وفي يوم عادي دائماً يبدو المشهد كهذا، لذا فأنتم لم ترونه بتاتاً.
It was insidious and it was really happening.
كانت تحدث غدراً وطوال الوقت.
Then I decided I had to get really smart,
وبعدها قررت أنني يجب أن أكون ذكياً،
I would take this job in the West Coast.
يجب أن أغتنم فرصة هذا العمل في الساحل الغربي.
And I moved to Redlands California.
وأنتقلت الى ريدلاندس في كاليفورنيا.
Very nice, and there
جميل جداً، وهناك
my older, senior lungs, as I like to call them,
رئتي العجوزتين، كما أحب تسميتهم،
I filled with particulate matter, carbon dioxide and very high doses of ozone.
أصبحت مليئة بالجسميات، ثاني أوكسيد الكربون، وجرعات عالية من الأوزون.
Okay? Almost like the highest in the nation.
حسناً؟ غالباً مثل الأعلى في البلاد.
Alright, this is what it looks like on a good day.
حسناً، هذا ما يبدو عليه الأمر في يوم جيد.
If you've been there, you know what I'm talking about.
إذا ذهبتم الى هناك، ستعرفون ما أتحدث عنه.
So, what's wrong with this picture?
إذاً، ما هو الخطأ في هذه الصورة؟
Well, the picture is, there is a huge gap here.
حسناً، هذه الصورة هي، هناك فجوة كبيرة هنا.
The one thing that never happens in my doctor's office:
الشئ الوحيد الذي لا يحدث في مكتب طبيبي:
They never ask me about my place history.
أنهم لا يسألون بتاتاً عن تاريخ أماكن عملي.
No doctor, can I remember, ever asking me,
لا يوجد طبيب، أستطيع أن أتذكره، سألني من قبل،
"Where have you lived?"
"أين عشت من قبل؟"
They haven't asked me what kind of the quality
لم يسألوني ما هي جودة
of the drinking water that I put in my mouth
مياة الشرب التي أشربها،
or the food that I ingest into my stomach.
أو الطعام الذي أستوعبه في معدتي.
They really don't do that. It's missing.
أنهم لا يفعلون ذلك حقاً. ان هذا الامر مفقود .
Look at the kind of data that's available.
أنظروا لنوعية البيانات المتاحة.
This data's from all over the world --
هذه البيانات من كل العالم--
countries spend billions of dollars investing in this kind of research.
بلدان صرفت مليارات الدولارات تستثمر في هذا النوع من البحوث.
Now, I've circled the places where I've been.
الآن، قمت بوضع دائرة في الأماكن التي كنت فيها.
Well, by design, if I wanted to have a heart attack
حسناً، تصميمي، إذا أردت أن أصاب بسكتة قلبية
I'd been in the right places. Right?
لقد ذهبت الى الأماكن المناسبة. صحيح؟
So, how many people are in the white?
إذاً، كم عدد الناس في الدائرة البيضاء؟
How many people in the room have spent the majority of their life
كم عدد الناس في هذه القاعة الذين قضوا حياتهم
in the white space?
في الفراغات البيضاء؟
Anybody? Boy you're lucky.
أي شخص؟ يا رجل أنت محظوظ.
How many have spent it in the red places?
كم منكم قضاها في الأماكن الحمراء؟
Oh, not so lucky.
أوه، لست محظوظاً.
There are thousands of these kinds of maps
هناك آلالاف من هذه الخرائط
that are displayed in atlases
التي تم عرضها في الأطلس
all over the world.
في كل العالم.
They give us some sense of what's going
إنها تعطينا فكرة عن ماذا يحدث
to be our train wreck.
لنصبح أمام صدمة قطار.
But none of that's in my medical record.
لكن لا شئ من هذا موجود في سجلي الطبي.
And it's not in yours either.
وليست موجودة في سجلك أيضاً.
So, here's my friend Paul.
لذا، هذا هو صديقي باول.
He's a colleague. He allowed his cell phone to be tracked
إنه زميلي. لقد أتاح لهاتفه النقال أن يكون متعقباً
every two hours, 24/7,
كل ساعتين، طوال الوقت،
365 days out of the year
كل الأيام طوال السنة،
for the last two years, everywhere he went.
خلال العامين الماضيين، أي مكان ذهب إليه.
And you can see he's been to a few places around the United States.
ويمكنكم رؤية أنه ذهب لأماكن قليلة حول الولايات المتحدة.
And this is where he has spent most of his time.
وها هنا حيث قضى معظم وقته.
If you really studied that you might have some clues
إذا قمتم بدراستها ربما تحصلون على بعض الأفكار
as to what Paul likes to do.
حول ماذا يحب باول أن يفعل.
Anybody got any clues? Ski. Right.
أي شخص توصل لأي فكرة؟ التزحلق على جليد. صحيح.
We can zoom in here, and we suddenly see
يمكننا تكبير الصورة هنا، وفجأة نرى
that now we see where Paul has really spent a majority of his time.
الآن أين قضى باول معظم أوقات حياته.
And all of those black dots are all of the
وكل هذه المربعات المنقطة هي كل
toxic release inventories
الإنبعاثات السامة
that are monitored by the EPA.
التي تراقبها وكالة حماية البيئة.
Did you know that data existed?
هل كنتم تعلمون أن هذه البيانات موجودة؟
For every community in the United States,
لكل مجتمع في الولايات المتحدة،
you could have your own personalized map of that.
يمكنكم الحصول على خارطتكم الشخصية لذلك.
So, our cell phones can now build a place history.
لذا، فيمكن لهواتفنا المحمولة أن تبني أي تاريخ للمكان.
This is how Paul did it. He did it with his iPhone.
هكذا فعلها باول. لقد فعلها بهاتفه الآي فون.
This might be what we end up with.
ربما هذا ما سننتهي إليه.
This is what the physician would have
هذا ما ينبغي للأطباء الحصول عليه
in front of him and her when we enter that exam room
أمام أي شخص عندما يدخل لغرفة الكشف
instead of just the pink slip that said I paid at the counter. Right?
بدلاً عن الزلة الوردية التي يقال أنني دفعت مقابلها في العداد. صحيح؟
This could be my little assessment.
قد يكون هذا تقييم صغير.
And he looks at that and he says,
وينظر لذلك ويقول،
"Whoa Bill,
"يا بيل،
I suggest that maybe you not decide,
أقترح أنك ربما لم تقرر،
just because you're out here in beautiful California,
لأنك فقط خارج هنا في كاليفورنيا الجميلة،
and it's warm every day,
والجو دافئ كل يوم
that you get out and run at six o'clock at night.
بحيث أنك تخرج وتجري في السادسة مساء.
I'd suggest that that's a bad idea Bill,
أقترح أن تلك فكرة سيئة يا بيل،
because of this report."
وفقاً لهذا التقرير."
What I'd like to leave you for are two prescriptions.
ما أرغب في ترككم معه هو وصفتين.
Okay, number one is, we must teach physicians
حسناً، الأولى، يجب أن نعلّم الأطباء
about the value of geographical information.
حول قيمة المعلومات الجغرافية.
It's called geomedicine. There are about a half a dozen programs in the world right now
إنها تسمى الطب الجغرافي. هناك حوالي نصف الكثير من البرامج في العالم حالياً
that are focused on this.
التي تركز على هذا.
And they're in the early stages of development.
وكلها في مراحلها الأولى من التطوير.
These programs need to be supported,
هذه البرامج تحتاج للدعم.
and we need to teach our future
ويجب أن نعلم أطباء
doctors of the world
المستقبل في العالم
the importance of some of the information
أهمية بعض هذه المعلومات
I've shared here with you today.
التي تقاسمتها معكم اليوم.
The second thing we need to do
الشئ الثاني الذي نحتاج لفعله
is while we're spending billions and billions
هو بينما ننفق مليارات الدولارات
of dollars all over the world
في كل العالم
building an electronic health record,
لبناء سجلات طبية إلكترونية،
we make sure we put a place history
يجب التأكد من وضع تاريخ للأماكن
inside that medical record.
داخل السجل الطبي.
It not only will be important for the physician;
إنها لن تكون فقط مهمة للأطباء.
it will be important for the researchers
كذلك ستكون مهمة للباحثين
that now will have huge samples to draw upon.
الذين لديهم الآن مجموعة ضخمة من العينات ليرسموا عليها.
But it will also be useful for us.
لكنها أيضاً ستكون مفيدة لنا.
I could have made the decision, if I had this information,
كان يمكن أن أتخذ قراراً، إذا كان لدي هذه المعلومات
not to move to the ozone capital
ليس بالإنتقال لعاصمة الأوزون
of the United States, couldn't I? I could make that decision.
في الولايات المتحدة. ألا يمكنني؟ يمكن أن أتخذ ذلك القرار.
Or I could negotiate with my employer
أو يمكن أن أتفاوض مع صاحب العمل
to make that decision
ليأخذ ذلك القرار
in the best interest of myself and my company.
من أجل مصلحتي ومصلحة شركتي.
With that, I would like to just say that Jack Lord said
مع ذلك، أرغب في القول أن جاك لورد قال
this almost 10 years ago.
هذا قبل 10 أعوام مضت تقريباً.
Just look at that for a minute.
أنظروا فقط لهذا لدقيقة.
That was what the conclusion
كانت تلك خلاصة
of the Dartmouth Atlas of Healthcare was about,
ما كان أطلس دارتموث للرعاية الصحية حوله،
was saying that we can explain the geographic variations
بالقول أننا لا نستطيع تفسير الفوارق الجغرافية
that occur in disease, in illness, in wellness,
التي تحدث في المرض، في العلل، في العافية،
and how our healthcare system actually operates.
وكيف يعمل نظام رعايتنا الصحية بالفعل.
That was what he was talking about
ذلك ما كان يتحدث عنه
on that quote.
في ذلك الإقتباس.
And I would say he got it right almost a decade ago.
وسأقول أنه فهمها صحيحاً قبل عقد مضى تقريباً.
So, I'd very much like to see us begin to
لذا، أرغب بشدة في رؤية الجميع يبدأون
really seize this as an opportunity to get this into our medical records.
في إغتنام الفرصة لتضمين هذا في سجلاتنا الطبية.
So with that, I'll leave you that
إذاً، سأترككم مع ذلك
in my particular view of view of health:
في وجهة نظري المحددة للصحة،
Geography always matters.
الجغرافيا دائماً مهمة.
And I believe that geographic information
وأعتقد أن المعلومات الجغرافية
can make both you and me very healthy. Thank you.
يمكن أن تجعلنا جميعاً أصحاء بشدة. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)